<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Concerning the remissness of the magistrate a  sermon preached in the parish-church of Bovey-Tracy, last Easter day in the afternoon / by Francis Stooke, M.A., and vicar thereof.</title>
            <author>Stooke, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5740bA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42684</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875586</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 38875586</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152419</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152419)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2296:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Concerning the remissness of the magistrate a  sermon preached in the parish-church of Bovey-Tracy, last Easter day in the afternoon / by Francis Stooke, M.A., and vicar thereof.</title>
                  <author>Stooke, Francis.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Sam. Darker and Sam. Farley, for Charles Yeo, John Pearce, and Philip Bishop, Booksellers in Exon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Exeter :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures:</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XVIII, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152419:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152419:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Concerning the Remiſſneſs of the Magiſtrate. A SERMON Preached in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Bovey-Tracy,</hi> LAST <hi>Eaſterday</hi> in the Afternoon.</p>
            <p>By <hi>FRANCIS STOOKE,</hi> M. A. And VICAR thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EXETER:</hi> Printed by <hi>Sam. Darker</hi> and <hi>Sam. Farley,</hi> for <hi>Charles Yeo, John Pearce,</hi> and <hi>Philip Biſhop,</hi> Bookſellers in <hi>Exon,</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152419:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152419:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE only occaſion of Printing this following Diſcourſe, is to vindicate My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and it, from the unchriſtian Calumnies and Reflections that are every day caſt upon us: It was not my Deſign in Preaching of it, nor is it ſo in Printing of it, to exaſperate any Man, but only to contribute what I could towards the ſuppreſſion of <hi>Vice</hi> and <hi>Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity:</hi> And in purſuance of His <hi>Majeſty</hi>'s Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, for preventing and puniſhing <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> I concluded the beſt means of effecting it, was to reprove the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsneſs</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:152419:3"/> of Magiſtrates, and to excite them to a diligent Execution of the Laws againſt notorious Offenders. And this I was moved to do from no other principle, but an hearty Zeal for the Honour of GOD, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>Religion;</hi> which are very much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed by the bold and unreſtrained com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Wickedneſs</p>
            <p>But inſtead of the Succeſs I intended and hoped for, it was condemned as a perſonal Reflection, and a very rude Treatment of the ſublime Dignity of the Magiſtrate; and a for: of Indigitation, to be preached only before one of them. Now, I do ſincerely proteſt, I had no ſuch intentions, and ſhould have done it as ſoon before a whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of that Order; and it may be with better acceptance, and leſs hatred, than now I have met with. I have therefore ventured to ſend it abroad into the World, to let Men ſee how much I am wrong'd, and how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly I have ſuffer'd in my Reputation, upon the account of it. I am conſcious enough of its being unworthy of an Impreſſion, and
<pb facs="tcp:152419:3"/> of my own inability for ſuch a performance, and ſhould have gladly declined the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking: but the perpetual inceſſant Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that are riſen againſt us, together with the terrible Threats, and falſe Reports that are given out, have conſtrained me to it; beſides which I know nothing could have prevailed with me to appear in publick: And all that I have to deſire of the <hi>Reader,</hi> is, that he will vouchſafe it a candid Cenſure, and give ſome allowance for the Occaſion.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:152419:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152419:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ACTS xviii. Ver. 17.</bibl>
                  <p>And <hi>Gallio</hi> cared for none of theſe things.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Words are a deſcription of the Carriage and Behaviour of a great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate towards the moſt intolerable Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Indignity that could be offered in his Preſence; no leſs than ſtriking, and lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing violent Hands upon a Perſon in open Court; a Crime of ſo heinous and culpable a Nature, that it is accounted Capital in ſome Courts, and would have been puniſhed with Death. But <hi>Gallio</hi> did not account it ſuch, nor ſhew ſo high a Reſentment of it, and took as little notice of it, as tho' it had been an innocent, or an indifferent Action: <hi>He cared for none of theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152419:5"/>
            <p>Indeed it is a matter of great Conſequence in all Governments to make choice of ſuch Magiſtrates as are impartial and couragious, active and reſolute in the execution of their Office; and will ſpare neither Friend nor Foe, where-ever they obſerve the Laws to be vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, or any Inſolencies or Outrages commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. This would be a means to ſuppreſs the preſent Diſorders, and to prevent the like au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious and rude Attempts for the future. This indeed is the original deſign of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy and Government, to reſtrain Men from doing Evil and Miſchief, and to keep them in Peace and good Order; and as often as any ſhall tranſgreſs and deviate from theſe Rules, to aſſign them a condign Puniſhment, according to the demerit of their Offences. And if this Method were duly obſerved, the World would not have that cauſe to cry out of Rapine, Extortion, Oppreſſion, Fraud and Injuſtice, that now it hath: the Rich would not grind the Faces of the Poor, nor the Poor have cauſe to complain of the Oppreſſion of the Rich; Superiors would not tyrannize over
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152419:5"/> their Inferiors, nor Inferiors murmur and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel againſt their Superiors. Vice would not be ſo bold and bare-faced, nor Prophaneneſs ſo common and reputable, but Peace and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs would go hand in hand, and a univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Piety and Juſtice would overſpread the Face of the whole Earth, and Righteouſneſs would run down our Streets as a mighty Stream.</p>
            <p>It is generally eſteemed a great Honour to be a Member of thoſe that make Laws; I am ſure it is a much greater to be one of thoſe that put them in execution: For, to what purpoſe are they made, if they are never executed? But 'tis much to be feared, there are too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny which are inveſted with this Power, are of the ſame Temper and Diſpoſition with <hi>Gallio, They care not for theſe things:</hi> Altho' the greateſt Indecencies and Diſorders are perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated in their Preſence, and to the very Face of them. The Apoſtle tells us that the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates Power was given them for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>To be a terror to thoſe that do evil, and an encouragement to thoſe that do well,</hi> Rom. 13. 3. And he ſuppoſeth the Sword to be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152419:6"/> born in vain, when the Magiſtrate is not the Miniſter of God in this reſpect, <hi>A revenger, to execute wrath upon him that doth evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what a Bleſſing would it be to this Nation, if all our Magiſtrates would reſolve upon this Courſe, Act in conformity to the Apoſtle's Rule; and be magnanimous and fearleſs in the execution of their Office in ſuch a manner as he here directs. But inſtead of that, may we not juſtly complain of a Cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Indifferency, Remiſsneſs and Neglect, in taking cognizance of, or Puniſhing Offences; and altho' they are many times Eye witneſſes and Ear-witneſſes to the fouleſt Vices and the greateſt Lewdneſs and Prophaneneſs, yet will they for all that, paſs by ſuch Actions, and ſhew as little reſentment of them, as the great Man did in the Text, who would not be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, altho' there could not be a greater oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion given, then for Men to revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their own Hands, and to offer Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to a Perſon in the Court of Judicature, and in the ſight of the Judge. And yet we read of ſome that did ſo, for the Greeks took
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152419:6"/> 
               <hi>Soſthenes,</hi> the chief Ruler of the Synagogue, and beat him before the Judgment-ſeat, <hi>And</hi> Gallio <hi>cared for none of theſe things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In diſcourſing on which Words, I ſhall do theſe three things;
<list>
                  <item>I. I ſhall treat of them particularly, and as they relate to <hi>Gallio.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. I ſhall conſider them in general, as they concern the whole Order of Magiſtrates.</item>
                  <item>III. I will ſhew what uſe and improvement may be made of them: And of theſe ſeverally.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>1. And firſt, let us obſerve them in their particular concern, as they relate to <hi>Gallio,</hi> who is ſaid here to care for none of theſe things; wherein we may inform our ſelves, 1<hi>st,</hi> Who this <hi>Gallio</hi> was; a chief Magiſtrate. 2<hi>dly,</hi> What was the Crime objected againſt him; Neglect and Remiſsneſs in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Office; he cared not for it. 3<hi>dly.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152419:7"/> Wherein the peccancy and culpableneſs of his Crime conſiſted; he was careleſs in theſe things, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> in things of the greateſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Importance.</p>
            <p>1. As to the Perſon here ſpoken of, <hi>Gallio,</hi> he was a chief Magiſtrate, no leſs than Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul of <hi>Achaia; viz.</hi> the Lord-Deputy of that Province, under <hi>Claudius Caeſar</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of <hi>Rome.</hi> This <hi>Gallio</hi> was a Roman by Birth, and of a noble Extraction; he was the great <hi>Seneca</hi>'s elder Brother, and a Man of great Eminency and Note in his time, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he could not be fit to manage ſuch a difficult Poſt as the Government of <hi>Achaia</hi> was, a Country very full of Factions and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the People of it very ſtubborn and headſtrong; and where they could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail by Law, and obtain their Purpoſes by Juſtice, they would fulfil them by Force and Violence; as appears by their beating a Man in the preſence of their Governour; a very rude and unmannerly Action.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152419:7"/>
            <p>2. But yet it did not move <hi>Gallio</hi> in the leaſt, he paſs'd it by, and took little or no No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it, or at leaſt, would not ſeem to do ſo; he would not concern himſelf on either ſide, but as they quarrelled, ſo they might agree again for him; it was all one to him whether they were Friends or Foes, ſo long as they were Loyal and Obedient to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> But however, this is cenſured by all Interpreters as a great Fault in him, and taken as a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Remark faſtned on him by the Spirit of God, and adjudged thereby, a careleſs Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and a very ill Man, <hi>becauſe he cared not for theſe things;</hi> but otherwiſe, of a very good Temper and Diſpoſition; for he is ſtiled by the Poet, <hi>Dulcem Gallionem,</hi> which imports no leſs. But whatever the Nature of the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, he thought it would be no Policy in him to take either part, and ſo far he was ſafe, for then he was aſſured he ſhould diſoblige neither ſide; but all this proceeded from a cowardly and puſillanimous ſpirit in him; for being newly entred upon his Government,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152419:8"/> probably he might be afraid of the Rabble. He knew not but the Jews, had he favoured <hi>St. Paul</hi>'s Cauſe, might have accuſed him as no Friend of <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s: And 'tis moſt likely the Greeks, had he reſcued <hi>Soſthenes</hi> out of their Hands, might in that boiſtrous Humor have ſerved him in the ſame kind. Therefore he concluded it the ſafeſt way to paſs it by, that ſo he might eſcape their Fury; and ſave himſelf in a whole skin.</p>
            <p>This was the Humor of our great Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate here in the Text, he cared not what Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olences and Outrages there were committed; nor undoubtedly, if Murther it ſelf had enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, would not have been much concerned, provided he could keep himſelf out of Harms way. But this Behaviour of his is ſo far from being commendable, or indeed juſtifiable, that it is very criminous and blamable, and deſerves to be branded with the ignominious Character of Cowardize and Popularity.</p>
            <p>3. But that which heightens his Crime, and makes it the more culpable yet, is that he was
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152419:8"/> of the ſame temper in all things, in every Complaint that came before him, and thoſe of the greateſt moment and importance; ſuch as Controverſies about Religion, as this is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſuppoſed to be: If he had been remiſs and indifferent in one particular caſe only, and that too but a ſmall and inconſiderable mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Crime had not been ſo great; but he cared for none of theſe things, ſmall nor great: he would not concern himſelf in any of them. Now by this general neglect and remiſsneſs of his, he did but encourage and enbolden them to do the like again, and to be the more inſolent and irreſiſtible for the future; had he put the Laws in execution, and puniſhed them as ſoon as they had offended, they would have been under ſome terrour and dread of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the like, or any other offence again; whereas the impunity of one Crime is not only taken for a toleration of that, but is alſo a temptation to another. And this was the fault with which <hi>Gallio</hi> was juſtly charged; he neglected the doing Juſtice upon one ſort of Offenders, and preſently he is diſturbed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152419:9"/> with the inſolencies and clamours of another; had he puniſhed the <hi>Jews</hi> for their Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, the <hi>Greeks</hi> would never have fallen up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Perſon in ſuch a violent manner, and beaten him in his preſence.</p>
            <p>You have heard what this <hi>Gallionian</hi> tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and diſpoſition was, and wherein the cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalneſs of it lay; which was the firſt thing undertaken to be ſhewn. And I think what is here alledged againſt this Magiſtrate in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, may with as great a truth be aſſerted of the generality of that Office: they are too careleſs and remiſs in the execution of their Authority, and are worthy of as great blame as <hi>Gallio,</hi> or any other of that Order: they care but little for theſe things; if they did, Sin would not ſo much abound.</p>
            <p>2<hi>ly.</hi> For the neglect of doing Juſtice upon Offenders, is one of the principal cauſes of that deluge of Vice and Immorality, which at this time overflows the World. And this is the general Propoſition deduceable from theſe Words, and the ſecond Point we are to ſpeak to.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152419:9"/>
            <p>And to confirm what is here aſſerted, I need go no farther than Experience; I ſay Daily Experience is a ſufficient Proof to this Purpoſe: But I ſhall not content my ſelf with this only, but ſhall aſſign you a Scriptural one; which is that of the old <hi>Eli,</hi> who we are told 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 18. had been Judge of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> forty Years; and behaved himſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly very well in the Office; for we hear no ill character fix'd upon him, but only too much gentleneſs and lenity, in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Office: but we find this was a juſt cauſe of incenſing the divine diſpleaſure againſt him, and of God's denouncing ſuch heavy Judgments againſt his Family. Nay the old Man, as ſoon as the Complaint came to his Ears of the profane and diſſolute lives of his Sons, he took particular notice of it, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately reprov'd them for it, ſaying unto them, <hi>Why do ye ſuch things? for I hear of your evil doings by all this People: Nay, my Sons, it is no good report that I hear; for ye make the old People to tranſgreſs.</hi> The good old Man ſeem'd to be heartily ſorry and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152419:10"/> troubled for his Sons follies, but this did not anſwer God's end: And he was offended with him for this reaſon, becauſe his Sons made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves vile, and he reſtrained them not. God expects more than mere words, and bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs; eſpecially where his Honour, and that of Religion are ſo much concerned. For when Profaneneſs, and Looſeneſs, and Irreligion crept in among them, and grew too hard for the Government, God threatens to do ſuch a thing in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> at which both the Ears of every one that heareth it ſhall tingle, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 11.</p>
            <p>Now the principal Reaſon why God enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſuch an indignation, and denounced this heavy judgment againſt the Houſe of <hi>Eli,</hi> was becauſe thoſe Crimes his Sons were guilty of, were of a very contagious nature, and might infect others, as well as themſelves; and by not reſtraining them, the whole land would ſoon be overrun with profaneneſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery. So that it was not <hi>Eli</hi>'s perſonal miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages that God thought himſelf ſo diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored by him; but for want of taking due care for the ſuppreſſion of Lewdneſs and Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152419:10"/> in others. And this ſhews us the true way how every Magiſtrate may beſt ſerve God In his Station, acquire the applauſe of being an Honour to God and his Profeſſion, and beſt anſwer the end of his Function; which is by giving all due encouragement to Religion and Vertue; and by a diligent application of the moſt effectual means for ſuppreſſing Irreligion, and Profaneneſs.</p>
            <p>This indeed is a great and noble Deſign, worthy of the greateſt Minds; and an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment fit for Perſons of the moſt celebrated Valour and Courage; and no way proper for Men of daſtardly and effeminate Spirits: For it muſt be acknowledged to be a work of ſome difficulty, to do this effectually. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much eaſier to ſubdue the Bodies, than the Paſſions of Men: For many are ſo wedded to their Luſts, that they account it as bad as Death to be ſeparated from them; and would rather mortify their Bodies in the Literal ſenſe, than to be depriv'd of their beloved Sin. For do we not daily ſee that Men will forgo Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Reputation, Intereſt, Health, and the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152419:11"/> hopes of Heaven, rather than thoſe Vices they have been accuſtomed to the practice of? It is in vain then to imagine, that the mere fears of the Execution of Human Laws ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently reſtrain thoſe, whom no fear of Hell or Damnation, could hitherto reform? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there may, no doubt, be a means found out how this bleſſed Deſign may be perfected; how Vice may be brought into Diſgrace, and Vertue become genteel and faſhionable: And there cannot be better expedient, than good Examples; eſpecially of thoſe who are Men of Fortune and Grandeur: Let ſuch as theſe ſet the Example, and there is no fear but they will ſoon be followed. For Vertue is as at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive as Vice, when it is recommended by the practice of Men of Riches and Authority: for whatever a Great Man practices, be it good or evil, it is mighty influential, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom fails of ſucceſs: For, for the moſt part, (I know not how) it ſtrikes Mens Eyes, and charms their Hearts and Affections into a Love firſt, and then into an Imitation of it.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152419:11"/>
            <p>But how powerful and efficacious ſoever great mens Examples may be to this purpoſe, yet this of it ſelf will not do with all; for meer Examples, altho' of excellent uſe to men of ingenious minds, yet to others, they are not ſo, but are likened to Mercury-poſts which ſtand in the Road and point to the right, but men will go which way they pleaſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>But if Examples will not do, ſurely Laws will; and it cannot be denied but that we have excellent Laws againſt Vice and Debauchery, and there is as great an Encouragement for the Execution of them as was ever known in any Reign. But yet there is a juſt Complaint of a mighty Deluge of all ſorts of Wickedneſs ſtill among us; Are not Drunkenneſs, and Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Unrighteouſneſs, and Oppreſſion, Propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Lord's day, and Contempt of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as common Vices now as ever? And don't we hear as horrid Oaths and tremendous Curſes, and as great a Plenty of them, as we heard before that excellent Act was made for the ſuppreſſing of theſe Vices? Nay, How
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152419:12"/> few of thoſe whoſe Concern it is to ſee it done, are ſo hearty and zealous in puniſhing of them as they are required to be? And what ſhould be the reaſon that there is no abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it all this while, eſpecially at a time when Gratitude, if not our holy Profeſſion, ſhould oblige us to a Reformation? Why, it is eaſie to reſolve all into the Corruption of human Nature; men are degenerated from the Vertues of their Anceſtors, and are become feral and brutiſh: but this is a general An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer which ſerves for all Times and Places, and may not be ſo peculiar to the preſent, but I ſhall aſſign one as much more probable and likely; which is, that the bad Examples of thoſe who ought to reform others, bring Vice into faſhion, and do thereby propagate and encreaſe the Practice of it. It is to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe therefore to talk of Laws, Religion, or Reformation, unleſs there be a Power made uſe of to reſtrain the Vices, alter the Cuſtoms, and change the Lives of Men.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152419:12"/>
            <p>Therefore to Examples and Laws the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate's Power muſt be added, which was originally ordained for this end; that is, to be both a Terror to thoſe that do Evil, as well as an Encouragement to thoſe that do well. And then the Apoſtle ſuppoſeth the Sword is not bore in vain, when the Magiſtrate is the Miniſter of God in this reſpect; <hi>a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doth evil.</hi> But if they ſuffer this bold Commiſſion of Sin to paſs without Correction, it will ere long pull down the Vengeance of God upon the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and cauſe him to rain Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone upon it, as he did upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrha,</hi> till it be conſum'd: And if it ſhould happen that this or any other terrible judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be our fate, where can we lay the blame? Will it not lay at the door of the Magiſtrates and Officers of Juſtice; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they might, but would not redreſs theſe Impieties. For it has always been an allow'd Maxim, That he who did not forbid Sin, when it was in his power, does in effect com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it. And he that doth not puniſh it,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152419:13"/> when it is in his power, encourages and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds it.</p>
            <p>But the great evil and miſchief of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate's Neglect, in doing juſtice upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Offenders, will more fully appear from theſe following Conſiderations; becauſe God is thereby diſhonoured, Religion diſparaged, the Government weakened, Authority diſpis'd, and Atheiſm increas'd.</p>
            <p>1<hi>st.</hi> Firſt, I ſay, God is thereby diſhonoured; when Vice and Immorality are countenanced, and tolerated in a Nation: or, which is all one, when they are conniv'd at, and uncorrected; Men will be apt to judge irreverently of God, and ſay, That if he do not take complacency and delight in ſuch actions, yet he is not very highly provoked and offended with them. For, if he was, he would either ſhower down an immediate Vengeance upon the actors, as he did upon <hi>Hophni</hi> and <hi>Phineas,</hi> who for their Immorality and Lewdneſs, were taken off both in one day: Or elſe, he would denounce an heavy judgment againſt thoſe, who had it in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152419:13"/> their power to reſtrain ſuch Indignities, and affronts to the Divine honour, and yet were ſo negligent as to over-look them; as he did to old <hi>Eli</hi> and his Houſe, ſo as utterly to can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel and extinguiſh it.</p>
            <p>Should <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels</hi> obſerve the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and how they eſcape without puniſhment, they would be apt to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain mean and unworthy notions of the <hi>Deity</hi> whom we worſhip; that he is an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure or careleſs Being, and unconcerned for his Honour; otherwiſe he would never ſuffer ſuch intolerable Abuſes againſt his Divine and Sacred Perſon. <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Purity</hi> are moſt eſſential to GOD; herein does his Image chiefly conſiſt, and whoever acts in conformity to theſe Vertues, bears the neareſt reſemblance to his <hi>Heavenly Father,</hi> and may (in ſome ſenſe) be ſaid to dignify and illuſtrate the <hi>Deity</hi> whom he adores. And it is ſo accounted even by GOD himſelf, who takes it as an Honour done unto Him; and has promis'd to compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſate ſuch ſervices with Honour, <hi>Thoſe that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me, I will honour with God;</hi> (i. e.) Thoſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152419:14"/> who by <hi>Holineſs</hi> of Life and purity of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, do profeſs to believe in me, ſuch as theſe I would chooſe for my Votaries; for they are an Ornament to the Religion they profeſs, and a credit to the <hi>Numen</hi> they adore: But they that deſpiſe me, ſhall be lightly eſteem'd, (i. e.) ſuch as profeſs to know GOD, but in their works deny him; who own a GOD, and yet live as if there were none; who give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to a profane and irreligious temper of Mind, and let looſe the reins to all ſorts of wickedneſs in their Lives, ſuch as the Sons of <hi>Eli</hi> were, who are ſaid to be the Sons of <hi>Belial;</hi> that lived without yoke or reſtraint, who knew not the <hi>Lord.</hi> 'Tis true, GOD cannot be deſpis'd for his glorious Perfections; yet his Authority may be diſpis'd, when Men preſumptiouſly break his Laws, and do not regard what he hath commanded or forbidden them. And ſeeing he hath appointed an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Men for this purpoſe, to ſee his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands executed, to puniſh Vice, and reward Vertue; he accounts it as a great affront done him, if they neglect it.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:152419:14"/>
            <p>2<hi>ly.</hi> And as GOD is highly diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, by ſuch a ſinful Neglect, ſo is Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion no leſs diſparaged and contemned. Some will be apt to take it for a cheat and impoſture, and ſay, It is impoſed upon Men for Secular and Politick ends, and no way conducive to the Honour of <hi>GOD,</hi> or the benefit of Souls. Whereas if the Magiſtrate did profeſs an aw and veneration for it, and act in conformity to his Profeſſion; then moſt Men, eſpecially ſuch as are dependent on him, would be brought by his Authority, or won by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, into a love and liking of it. But when Magiſtrates are careleſs and indifferent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, it makes others ſo too; and renders Religion as a mean and contemptible thing: When thoſe whoſe main Duty it is to look af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, who are conſtituted Guardians and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of it, do ſlight and neglect it, and will not concern themſelves in reſtraining Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality and Profaneneſs, the great blemiſhes of Religion; then will Men be apt to ſlight and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule it, and account it a thing of indifferency whether they are ſubſervient to it, or no.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152419:15"/>
            <p>3<hi>ly.</hi> But this is not all; their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt does not ſtop here; they will at laſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe Authority it ſelf: What an inſignificant thing is Power and Superiority, if it be not employed to the uſes for which it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained? And where it is not duly executed, it will at length be ſlighted and deſpiſed: It is a true Saying, Too much Familiarity breeds Contempt; but never more true than in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry;</hi> a too great Freedom and Familiariry of Converſation, does very much depreciate and degrate theſe ſubblime and honourable Functions, and makes them diſeſteemed and neglected: whereas Strangeneſs and Diſtance, will create a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rential Aw and Deference in all acceſſes to them, and preſerve that Honour and Dignity, which is juſtly owing to their Character.</p>
            <p>4<hi>ly.</hi> Another evil Conſequence of <hi>Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsneſs</hi> and <hi>Remiſsneſs</hi> in the <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> is, becauſe the Government is very much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and made impotent thereby. The Sins of a Nation do naturaly tend the weakneſs and diſhonour of it: Profaneneſs, Debauchery,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152419:15"/> and Vice, are not only the reproach of a People, but they are the readieſt means to deſtroy it: who can deny that Luxury, Debauchery, and all ſorts of Intemperance, not only ſink the Reputation of a People; but alſo ſoftens and effeminates them, and makes them careleſs, idle and regardleſs of any thing, but what conduces to Eaſe and Voluptuouſneſs. In all probability, ſuch a Nation cannot ſtand long; eſpecially if it chance to be encountred by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other of more Wiſdom, Courage and Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it will ſoon be overcome by it. So that it is plain, that ſuch Sins as theſe have a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural efficacy in them of weakening the Power and Intereſt of a Kingdom. But there are other Sins, ſuch as Profaneneſs, Contempt of GOD and Religion, common Swearing, Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy, Lying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are the moral cauſes of a Nation's Ruin; and when the meaſure of the People's Iniquity is filled up, it will accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſucceed with them; as it did with the <hi>Jews,</hi> who are now a <hi>Lo-ammi,</hi> that is, no more a People.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:152419:16"/>
            <p>5<hi>ly.</hi> The fifth and laſt evil Conſequence of Remiſsneſs in the Magiſtracy, is, that Sin is thereby increaſed and propagated; he that does not dread the power of a Magiſtrate, will make but little conſcience of his Actions, but indulge himſelf in his Lewdneſs with all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable freedom and licentiouſneſs, and ſuffer nothing to reſtrain him, till he has gone thro' all the claſſes of Impiety, and is become a great proficient in it: and having drown'd his Senſes and his Reaſon, he is at laſt tempted to ſay with the fool in the <hi>Pſalm, There is no God.</hi> And the Conſequence of that, is to be corrupt and abominable, or to commit all Unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with greedineſs, in the <hi>Apoſtle</hi>'s phraſe. This is the pernicious effect of Sin, if it be not timely reſtrained and prevented: It is of ſo contagious and ſpreading a nature, that it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently infects the whole Neighbourhood, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes it ſelf from City to Country, and at laſt becomes Epidemical.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome of the miſchievous Effects of <hi>Remiſsneſs</hi> in the <hi>Magiſtracy;</hi> by which it evidently appears to be moſt true, what was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152419:16"/> aſſerted in the general Propoſition, That the Neglect of doing Juſtice upon Offenders, is one of the principal cauſes of that deluge of Vice and Immorality, which at this time over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flows the World.</p>
            <p>Now the Application is as follows: If this then be the Cauſe of moſt of the Sin and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety that abounds in the World, it does cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly then very much concern all the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, and Officers of Juſtice among us in this Kingdom, to uſe all due care to prevent the growth and increaſe of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs. Let them abandon that Popular and lukewarm Temper (which has been the cauſe of ſo much miſchief, both to Church and State, for the future, and be more active and diligent in their Office; eſpecially where the Glory of GOD, and the Intereſt of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion are ſtruck at: they ſhould bluſh to be found remiſs and negligent in Executing the Laws, upon willful and notorious Offenders. To do ſo, is an argument they are too much in love with Sin themſelves; otherwiſe they
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152419:17"/> would be more careful to puniſh it in others. I wiſh I could lift up my Voice, and ſpeak loud enough to awaken every one of them, and perſwade them to be diligent and vigilant in their Office; to chaſtiſe all publick Offenders, and do Juſtice ſtrictly upon thoſe who diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <hi>GOD,</hi> and are a ſcandal to Religion. Stir up your ſelves, and be zealous for your. <hi>GOD,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaks. Let not the Drunkards, the Blaſphemers, the profaners of the Lord's-day, who deſpiſe his Worſhip and Service, go unpuniſhed. Be juſt and impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial in all your Corrections; ſpare neither Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative, nor Dependent; let your Indignation be extended againſt Sin in general, and as often as you find it perpetrated, be ſure to puniſh it. Diſcountenance Make-bates, and ſowers of Diſcord among Brethren: reprove the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane and Common-ſwearer, and lay the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty as often as you find him to offend. In a word, let the ſeverity of the Law be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted againſt all open Wickedneſs.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:152419:17"/>
            <p>And this indeed would be the moſt effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual way, to produce a Reformation through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole Kingdom. This would be the readieſt way to make us an happy People. For tho' there might ſtill be a great many ſins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted amongſt us, in ſecrecy and under covert; yet they would not be National Sins, nor be imputed to us as a publick Guilt; but every Man ſhould bear his own Iniquity. Whereas without ſuch a Reformation as this, or an hearty and an honeſt Endeavour after it, all our Pretences to Religion, will ſerve only as ſo many marks of our Inſincerity, and of the mean Opinion we have of <hi>GOD;</hi> as if he would be moved with ſuch Services, wherein we preſent Him only the form and ſurface, and neglect the weightier concern of doing Juſtice, ſhewing Mercy, and walking humbly before Him. There cannot be a greater diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour done to His Divine Majeſty, than to be unconcerned at the great Scandal that is caſt upon Religion, by a bold and publick Profaneneſs, and to ſuffer it to eſcape with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out check or puniſhment.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152419:18"/>
            <p>It will be to no purpoſe for Miniſters, to decry Vice in their Sermons, nor to divert from it in their Lives, if the Magiſtrate's Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity do not ſecond their Endeavours; for let them do the one never ſo powerfully, and the other never ſo regularly, yet it will be all in vain, without the concurrence of the Magiſtrate's Sword, to terrify and reſtrain them from Vice, and over-awe and compel them to Obedience.</p>
            <p>And this is no private conjecture, or groundleſs ſurmiſe; but the wiſdom of the Nation has concluded this to be the moſt ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual means of ſuppreſſing that flood of Sin and Impiety, that at this time over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreads the Kingdom; and have rightly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged the cauſe of it to be want of Care and Diligence in the Magiſtrate, of putting the Laws in execution.</p>
            <p>As you would therefore anſwer the great Ends of your ſublime Order, omit no op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of doing all that is conduceable
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152419:18"/> thereunto: uſe your utmoſt Power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Honour of <hi>GOD,</hi> and the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Religion: And this cannot be better done, than by diſcountenancing all lewd and vicious Perſons, and encouraging the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous and Good. And above all, be moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to avoid all the kinds, nay, and the very appearance of evil in your Lives and Actions: Conſider the Dignity of your Character; the Scripture calls you Gods; and ſure to anſwer that Character your muſt not only refrain your ſelves from all Wickedneſs in general, but alſo be eminent and exemplary in all holy Converſation and Godlineſs. <hi>Let your Light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glory your Father which is in Heaven.</hi> And let us conſtantly pray, as our Church directs in that pertinent branch of her <hi>Litany,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">That <hi>GOD</hi> would be pleas'd to bleſs and keep the Magiſtrates, giving them Grace to execute Juſtice, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Truth.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152419:19"/>
            <p>And to cloſe up all, let me exhort and beſeech you, in the words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> That <hi>every one that nameth the Name of</hi> CHRIST, <hi>would depart from Iniquity:</hi> As we expect the Bleſſing of Heaven upon us, and wiſh the Happineſs of theſe Kingdoms, and that the great work of Reformation may go ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully on; let us every one in our ſeveral Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, Stations and Places, ſet our ſelves ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly againſt Vice and Wickedneſs, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to root it out. For not only our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, but our Eternal Intereſt is depending on it: <hi>Which GOD give us all Grace to do, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152419:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
